Finding Aid for Katharine Tennyson Papers, 1969-1973
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Katharine Tennyson papers 1969-1973
Tennyson, Katharine.
0.5 linear feet
0535 Aa 2
Katharine Tennyson was a nurse in Detroit, Michigan, who was an activist supporting reform of Michigan abortion laws in the early 1970s. The collection documents her work with various organizations, especially the Michigan Abortion Referendum Committee.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The papers were received from Lee Kefauver (donor no. 8760 ) and came to the library in 2005.
The collection is open to research.
In 1969, a Detroit area coalition organized to work to repeal Michigan's abortion law. The Michigan Organization for the Repeal of Abortion Laws (MORAL) included, among other participants, the YWCA, Unitarian-Universalist Church Women, National Association of Social Workers, National Council of Jewish Women, Women's Liberation Movement, and New Democratic Coalition. MORAL, through a petition campaign and lobbying the state legislaature sought to influence abortion-related legislation. Kathy Tennyson was active in MORAL as well as the Michigan Women for Medical Control of Abortion.
Tennyson participated as an area coordinator for abortion reform in Wayne County, assisting the Detroit Women's Abortion Action Coalition (DWAAC) and the Women's National Abortion Action Coalition (WONAAC). DWAAC supported abortion reform and a class action law suit for the repeal of Michigan abortion law. The Michigan Coordinating Committee for Abortion Reform launched a petition drive for abortion reform in 1971 in which Tennyson participated. Michigan Women's Abortion Suit, having initiated a class action suit in June 1971, was also promoted and supported by Tennyson in Wayne County. Tennyson's activity through DWAAC brought her into contact with the Michigan Abortion Referendum Committee (MARC). In 1972 Proposal B, the abortion reform referendum, was put on the November ballot and Tennyson was the MARC Wayne County Petition Drive Coordinator, urging support of Proposal B. In 1972, Tennyson organized the Michigan Abortion Referendum Committee - Wayne County Chapter as a mechanism for the petitioning and fund-raising efforts.
State Senator, Gilbert Bursley, was chairman of the MARC Executive Committee and introduced abortion reform legislation in the State Senate. Despite his support and that of Governor and Mrs. Milliken and Michigan Secretary of State, Richard Austin, Proposal B was defeated in the November 7, 1972 election.
The Katharine Tennyson papers are divided into two series: Early Organizations and Michigan Abortion Referendum Committee.
Subjects:
Abortion--Michigan.; Abortion--Law and legislation--Michigan.; Michigan Abortion Referendum Committee.; Michigan Organization for the Repeal of Abortion Laws.; Michigan--Politics and government--1951-; Michigan--Politics and government--1971-1980.; Pro-choice movement--Michigan.; Tennyson, Katharine.; Women's rights--Michigan.
- Early Organizations
  Early Organizations series includes notes on meetings, flyers, and some budget information on MORAL, DWAAC, Michigan Coordinating Committee for Abortion Reform, and Michigan Abortion Law Suit.
  - Michigan Organization for the Repeal of Abortion Laws (MORAL), 1969-1970 (Box 1)
  - Detroit Women's Abortion Action Coalition (DWAAC), 1971 (Box 1)
  - Women's National Abortion Action Coalition (WONAAC) (Box 1)
  - Michigan Coordinating Committee for Abortion Reform, 1971-1972 (Box 1)
  - Michigan Abortion Law Suit, 1971-1972 (Box 1)
- Michigan Abortion Referendum Committee (MARC)
  Michigan Abortion Referendum Committee series includes notes on meetings, flyers, budgets for the Lansing organization and correspondence, DBA, financial information, and minutes and notes for the Wayne County Chapter.
  - MARC Lansing, 1972-1973 (Box 1)
  - MARC Wayne County Chapter
    - Correspondence, 1971-1973 (Box 1)
    - DBA and lease, 1972 (Box 1)
    - Financial records, 1972 (Box 1)
    - Job Description, county coordinator (Box 1)
    - Minutes and notes, 1971-1972, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - State program information, 1972 (Box 1)
    - Wayne County Petition Drive income and expense, 1972 (Box 1)